Brian Keith Norambuena

Assistant Professor
Department of Computing and Systems Engineering
Universidad Católica del Norte, Antofagasta, Chile
brian.keith@ucn.cl | Personal Webpage | Google Scholar

Summary

I am an Assistant Professor at the Department of Computing and Systems Engineering at Universidad Católica del Norte in Antofagasta, Chile. My research interests lie at the intersection of visualization, artificial intelligence, and computational narratives. However, I am also broadly interested in visual analytics, natural language processing, and data science. My current work focuses on the extraction and visualization of computational narratives using interactive narrative maps based on artificial intelligence techniques.

Education

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA, USA.

Ph.D. in Computer Science and Applications

Aug 2019 - Aug 2023

Dissertation: Narrative Maps: A Computational Model to Support Analysts in Narrative Sensemaking

Advisors: Dr. Chris North and Dr. Tanushree Mitra

GPA: 4.0/4.0

Universidad Católica del Norte, Antofagasta, Chile.

Master's in Informatics Engineering

Mar 2016 - Aug 2017

Thesis: Hybrid machine learning methods for multiclass sentiment analysis.

GPA: 6.9/7.0

Bachelor of Mathematics

Mar 2012 - Aug 2017

Thesis: Applications of spectral graph theory in artificial neural networks.

GPA: 6.7/7.0

Professional Title: Computing and Informatics Civil Engineering

Mar 2010 - Aug 2016

Bachelor of Science in Engineering

Thesis: Opinion mining and sentiment analysis applied to paper reviews.

GPA: 6.7/7.0

<u>Funding</u>

• Co-researcher in the *CONICYT Project* "Bayesian multidimensional classifiers for emotion interpretation in text and video" in charge of Dr. Juan Bekios-Calfa. Project code: REDI170607.

Publications

Journal Publications

- "A survey on event-based news narrative extraction", B. Keith, T. Mitra & C. North, ACM Computing Surveys, 2023.
- "An extension of the characteristic curve model of plant species behavior in heavy metal soils", E. Lam, **B. Keith**, J. Bech, M. Gálvez, R. Rojas, F. Alvarez, V. Zetola & I. Montofré, *Environmental Geochemistry and Health*, 2023.
- "Design guidelines for narrative maps in sensemaking tasks", B. Keith, T. Mitra & C. North, Information Visualization, 2022.

- "Evaluating semantic representations for extended association rules", L. Gutiérrez & B. Keith, Intelligent Data Analysis, 2022.
- "Characteristic curve modeling of plant species behavior in soils with heavy metals", E. Lam, **B. Keith**, J. Bech, F. Alvarez, V. Zetola, L. Pereira & I. Montofré, *Environmental Geochemistry and Health*, 2022.
- "Twitter sentiment analysis for the estimation of voting intention in the 2017 Chilean elections", T. Alegre & **B. Keith**, *Intelligent Data Analysis*, 2022.
- "Using Artificial Intelligence Techniques to Improve the Prediction of Copper Recovery by Leaching", V. Flores, B. Keith
 & C. Leiva, Journal of Sensors, 2020.
- "Effect of pretreatment prior to leaching on a chalcopyrite mineral in acid media using NaCl and KNO3", V. Quezada, A. Roca, O. Benavente, M. Cruells, **B. Keith** & E Melo, *Journal of Materials Research and Technology*, 2020.
- "An extension to association rules using a similarity-based approach in semantic vector spaces", **B. Keith** & C. Meneses, *Intelligent Data Analysis*, 2019.
- "Heurísticas para Data Augmentation en NLP: Aplicación a Revisiones de Artículos Científicos", R. Sánchez, C.
 Meneses & B. Keith, Revista Ibérica de Sistemas e Tecnologias de Informação, 2019.
- "Gradient Boosted Trees Predictive Models for Surface Roughness in High-Speed Milling in the Steel and Aluminum Metalworking Industry", V. Flores & **B. Keith**, *Complexity*, 2019.
- "Using the Belbin method and models for predicting the academic performance of engineering students", L. Gutiérrez, V. Flores, **B. Keith**, A. Quelopana, *Computer Applications in Engineering Education*, 2019.
- "Necessity of intervention policies for tailings identified in the Antofagasta Region, Chile", E. Lam, **B. Keith**, Í. Montofré & M. Gálvez, *Revista Internacional de Contaminación Ambiental*, 2019.
- "Copper Uptake by Adesmia atacamensis in a Mine Tailing in an Arid Environment", E. Lam, B. Keith, Í. Montofré & M. Gálvez, Air, Soil and Water Research, 2018.
- "Evaluation of soil intervention values in mine tailings in northern Chile", E. Lam, B. Keith, Í. Montofré & M. Gálvez, PeerJ, 2018.
- "Assessment of the adaptive capacity of plant species in copper mine tailings in arid and semiarid environments", E.
 Lam, M. Gálvez, M. Cánovas, Í. Montofré, B. Keith, Journal of Soils and Sediments, 2018.
- "Minería de procesos de software: una revisión de experiencias de aplicación", B. Keith & V. Vega, Revista Ibérica de Sistemas e Tecnologias de Informação, 2017.
- "Evaluation of the phytoremediation potential of native plants growing on a copper mine tailing in northern Chile", E. Lam, M. Cánovas, M. Gálvez, Í. Montofré, **B. Keith**, Á. Faz, *Journal of Geochemical Exploration*, 2017.
- "A Knowledge-Based Prototype to Support the Intelligent Diagnosis of High-Risk Pregnancy", V. Flores, **B. Keith**, D. Poblete, C. Leiva, *Applied Medical Informatics*, 2017.

Book Chapters

"Avances en representaciones de texto: espacios vectoriales semánticos y word embeddings", L. Gutiérrez & B. Keith, presented at CILCC 2018 and published as a book chapter on "Tecnologías del lenguaje humano", 2020.

Conference Publications (peer-reviewed, full papers)

- "Narrative Maps: An Algorithmic Approach to Represent and Extract Information Narratives", B. Keith & T. Mitra, CSCW 2021, USA.
- "Mixed Multi-Model Semantic Interaction for Graph-based Narrative Visualizations", **B. Keith**, T. Mitra & C. North, *IUI 2023*, Australia.
- "Explainable Interactive Projections for Image Data", H. Han, R. Faust, B. Keith, R. Prabhu. T. Smith, S. Li & C. North,

- ISVC 2022, USA.
- "Narrative Maps: An Algorithmic Approach to Represent and Extract Information Narratives", **B. Keith** & T. Mitra, *CSCW* 2021, USA.
- "Extended association rules in semantic vector spaces for sentiment classification", B. Keith & C. Meneses, WorldCIST 2018, Italy.
- "Integration of Process Mining and Simulation: A Survey of Applications and Current Research", B. Keith, WorldCIST 2018, Italy.
- "The Scientific Landscape of Agile Software Development and Methodologies: A Social Network Analysis Perspective", **B. Keith** & V. Vega, *JIISIC 2018*, Chile.
- "Empirical Evaluation of the BCOC Method on Multi-Domain Sentiment Analysis Data Sets", **B. Keith** & C. Meneses, *CIARP 2018*, Spain.
- "Effect of curing time on the dissolution of a secondary copper sulphide ore using alternative water resources", V.
 Quezada, L. Velásquez, A. Roca, O. Benavente, E. Melo, B. Keith, IOP Conference Series: Materials Science and Engineering, 2018.
- "A Multilabel Extension of LDA Based on the Gram-Schmidt Orthogonalization Procedure", J. Bekios & B. Keith, CIARP 2017, Chile.
- "A Systematic Literature Review on Word Embeddings", L. Gutiérrez & B. Keith, CIMPS 2018, México.
- "A Review on Bayesian Networks for Sentiment Analysis", L. Gutiérrez, J. Bekios & B. Keith, CIMPS 2018, México.
- "Process mining applications in software engineering", **B. Keith** & V. Vega, *CIMPS 2016*, México.

Workshop Papers, Conference Short Papers, Unindexed Publications, and Posters

- "Characterizing Social Movement Narratives in Online Communities: The 2021 Cuban Protests on Reddit", B. Keith, T. Mitra & C. North, C+J 2022, USA.
- "Narrative sensemaking: strategies for narrative maps construction", B. Keith, T. Mitra & C. North, IEEE VIS 2021, USA.
- "Evaluating the Inverted Pyramid Structure through Automatic 5W1H Extraction and Summarization", B. Keith, M. Horning & T. Mitra, C+J 2020, USA.
- "The relevance of hyper-parameters in convolutional neural networks: a case study with Fashion-MNIST", R. Sánchez & **B. Keith**, *WDKE-INFONOR 2018*, Chile.
- "The LapRLS Algorithm as a Simple Approach to Sentiment Analysis Lexicon Construction", B. Keith & I. Jirón, WDKE-INFONOR 2018, Chile.
- "Twitter Sentiment Analysis applied to the 2017 Chilean Elections", T. Alegre & B. Keith, WDKE-INFONOR 2018, Chile.
- "A Hybrid Approach for Sentiment Analysis Applied to Paper Reviews", **B. Keith**, E. Fuentes & C. Meneses, *WISDOM at SIGKDD 2017*, Canada.
- "Barycentric coordinates for ordinal sentiment classification", B. Keith & C. Meneses, WISDOM at SIGKDD 2017, Canada.
- "A Comparative Review of Hybrid Methods for Multiclass Sentiment Analysis", B. Keith & C. Meneses, INFONOR 2016, Chile.

Invited Talks

- "Narrative maps: extraction and visualization of interactive narratives and applications", Workshop on Data and Knowledge Engineering, Universidad Católica del Norte, *INFONOR 2023*, Chile.
- "Mapas narrativos: extracción y visualización de narrativas interactivas y sus aplicaciones", ACHIRP, 2023, Chile.
- "Introduction to Sentiment Analysis and an Application to Scientific Paper Reviews", Workshop on Data and Knowledge Engineering, Universidad de Tarapacá, *INFONOR 2017*, Chile.
- "Aplicaciones de minería de procesos en la mejora de procesos de software", Workshop on Software Process Improvement, Universidad de Atacama, INFONOR 2016, Chile.

Teaching Experience

Instructor, Universidad Católica del Norte, Antofagasta, Chile.

- Introduction to Data Science: 2017/2, 2018/2.
- Foundations of Computing: 2017/2 to 2019/1.
- Probability & Statistics: 2016/2, 2017/1.
- Automata Theory & Formal Languages: 2016/1
- Analysis & Design of Algorithms: 2015/2 to 2017/1.
- Compilers: 2015/2, 2016/2, 2017/2, 2018/2.

Awards and Honors

- COE Pratt International Scholarship, Virginia Tech, 2023.
- Becas Chile Doctoral Studies Scholarship, CONICYT, 2019 2023.
- Fulbright Faculty Development Scholarship, Fulbright Chile, 2019 2021.
- Valedictorian of the 2017 Graduating Class, Faculty of Sciences, Universidad Católica del Norte.
- Valedictorian of the 2016 Graduating Class, Faculty of Engineering and Geological Sciences, Universidad Católica del Norte.
- "Alumno Destacado UCN" (Best Student of the University), Universidad Católica del Norte, 2013.
- "Alumno Destacado DISC" (Best Student of the Department), Department of Computing and Systems Engineering, Universidad Católica del Norte, 2012.

Professional Service

Editorships

Associate Editor: *Intelligent Data Analysis*, 2023 - Present Editorial Board: Intelligent Data Analysis, *2019* - Present.

Conference Organizing Committees

• International Conference on Computing and Informatics in North of Chile (INFONOR-CHILE), 2019.

Workshops Organized

Workshop on Data and Knowledge Engineering at INFONOR-CHILE (WDKE), 2017, 2018.

Technical Program Committee

- International Conference on Computing and Informatics in North of Chile (INFONOR-CHILE), 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, 2023.
- International Conference on Recent Trends in Image Processing & Pattern Recognition (RTIP2R), 2018, 2020.

Technical Reviewer

• Journals:

- Journal on Artificial Intelligence, 2023.
- o Computers, Materials & Continua, 2023.
- Current Bioinformatics, 2023.
- Resources, Conservation & Recycling, 2023.
- o Arabian Journal of Chemistry, 2021, 2023.
- o ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems, 2022.
- o Imaging Science Journal, 2022.
- o Computer Applications in Engineering Education, 2018, 2020.
- o Informatics in Medicine Unlocked, 2019.
- o Scientometrics, 2019.
- Socio-Economic Planning Science, 2020.
- Intelligent Data Analysis, 2018.

Conferences:

- ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (ACM FAccT), 2023.
- o Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (CogSci), 2023.
- o International Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), 2023.
- o ACM Conference On Computer-Supported Cooperative Work And Social Computing (CSCW), 2021.

Sub-reviewer:

International Joint Conference on Rough Sets (IJCR), 2016, 2017.